okay guys I'm going to just roll through
a bunch of stuff about box squats
because there's a lot of confusion uh
with the box squat exercise um there's a
lot of different types of box squats so
here are the four main ones but it
really depends on depth um which I'll go
over in a minute but uh there's the
squat Tu a box in this case you're just
you know you have a bar on your back and
you're just using it to gauge depth so
you just tap so this you use it as a way
to ensure that you're hitting the depth
that you want so you could set it to
make sure that you're hitting parallel
for example as you can see right here if
I do
this I'm just making parallel so if I've
got a bar on my back you know I tap come
up and with this style I don't
necessarily have to sit back with this
style I can just use my same you know my
knees can come forward and I can just
use my same squat style you know but I
just let the knees come forward and I
just tap come back up you don't ever
want to bounce but you you go like this
tap come up and this way you don't cheat
on your depth so that's a squat to a box
I don't consider that a box squat now on
most the different types of box squat
you can uh with to to me a box squat you
pause on the box and the reason why is
you break up the concentric you know the
Ecentric to concentric chain or whatever
you want to call it and you pause for a
second you will relax the hip and thigh
muscles so like the glutes the quads the
hammies the adductors you'll relax these
thigh and hip muscles but you keep the
Erectors on you don't relax the Erectors
and round so you keep the chest up now
you could come
down pause for a second don't rock at
all and then come back up or you can do
my favorite style the slight rock where
you come down rock come back up it's
just a slight rocking or you can do the
full Rock which would be come down lean
in come
up and talk to different coaches and
they'll all tell you why they prefer one
style over another I can make a case
really in the grand scheme of things is
it going to make a huge uh difference in
in terms of adaptations I don't think so
but I recommend you try all the
different styles now real quick I'm
going to go over the rocking
style for me trying to get from a side
view here you come back and if you do
the full rock you will come back like
this but you don't ever round your back
you keep this arched okay so you come
back lean in come back up now I used to
think that because box
squats involve so much sitting
back that they were very hip dominant
and I still think they're very hip
dominant especially with vertical tibia
so when you do a box squat you want The
Shins vertical and this is very hard for
a lot of people when you teach this to
beginners here's how I teach it to
beginners I actually have them get their
calves touching the Box okay C touching
the box and then because I like that
tactile feedback when I've got a bar on
I don't want to know if I'm going to hit
the box or not if if I might miss the
Box you don't want to be out here and
just wonder I hope the box is underneath
me you don't want to any feel like that
if it's touching you you know it's there
and then you got to reach back so I say
pretend someone has a rope around your
hips and they are pulling back so you
initiate with a sitting back motion then
you come down and bend the knees and
keep the knees out so it looks like this
again I have this I have
this my clients diagonal with it so this
part comes up they're straddling it
initiate by sitting back just a slight
like this not like they're not bending
forward at the knees so they're not
breaking at the knees they break at the
hips just slightly and then they descend
knees out sit way back now my shins are
pretty ver vertical here
almost it is possible to get a negative
angle meaning I sit so far back
that my tibas are actually angled this
way like that okay but I don't think you
can do that with a ton of weight and if
you do it and your shins are just
slightly forward a little bit that's
okay too A lot of people just can't get
the complete vertical shins maybe due to
their anthropometry that's not a deal
killer what matters is that you learn
how to go like this so youall got a bar
on my back I come back what you'll see
with beginners is they'll go they'll
want to go like this and they want to
have their knees about lined up with the
front of their
feet so what you want to do is tell them
not sit back more sit back more and
they'll
go no knees came forward so I'll sit in
front of them I'll get right down here
and I'll put my hands right here
blocking their knees sit backward sit
backward and what you'll see is they'll
do that they'll sit back they'll sit
back and then
give and they let off and they plop they
don't have the strength to control right
here but it's really when you get the
strength to do it this is a very
powerful position right here right here
um so they need to develop that strength
and you tell them don't plop don't plop
and you'll see people they'll come down
and they'll plop you don't want that
don't plop Pretend This is made of nails
and you're trying to tap it as lightly
as possible say come down tap come up
come down and I like the slight Rock but
see how it's a gentle soft
Landing okay now earlier I talked about
how hip dominant this is because you do
keep you know you keep the vertical
shins and you get a wide stance and you
sit back
but uh
Swinton a researcher I believe out of
the UK found that this has actually had
greater knee EXT in in
torqus than traditional or Olympic style
squatting and the reason why is because
people rocked back but as they rocked
forward they actually Rose off the Box
before the bar was centered over the mid
feet so when you do a nonbox squat the
bar will stay centered over the mid
feet but when you do the box
squat people will start to rise up right
here before the bar center of the mid
feet
so think of like so anyway it what it
does is it makes it more more of a knee
exercise and less of a hip so it's still
it's still hip dominant but depending on
how you do it and what I find is when I
go really heavy what I find is I end
up having to lean a lot and I lean in
and then I come up but this is such a
good exercise to teach
beginners the argument with raw
powerlifters is that you want
specificity specificity specificity so
if you compete in powerlifting most of
your time you should be free squatting
but I do believe that the even for raw
power lifs they should do box squat
sometimes it's such a valuable exercise
from the from straight on what I want to
show you is how this looks notice I do
not come down like this my knees are out
tracking over the feet so my femur is
right in line with tracking the same way
as my feet and so right here this is not
a good position even though my knees are
out because I'm not vert I don't have
vertical shins so I need to be here
right here like this okay so it looks
like this and what you have to tell
people is you're going to lean more
because you're sitting back so far so if
if I keep vertical shins I have to lean
I can't be upright while keeping
vertical shins I fall backwards now this
this is all everything I've taught you
is for the parallel box squat for the
high box squat this is about uh I
believe this
is 15 in high it could be 16 in you know
what I think it's 16 in high and the
lowest setting is 11 in high
now 16 in high works for a lot of people
for the parallel position and I'll show
you with the barbell what it looks like
so get into position and I like low bar
with these but you can still use high
bar so you can put the bar up here and
use high bar but since you're sitting
back so much I think it's wiser to do
low bar keep it right around here see
that I have contact my back of my calves
are touching the box I am I'm not U
right like this I have a slight lean
already I initiate by sitting back knees
out tap come up now I'm going to do a
slight
Rock so I'm going to come around here
and show you from straight on what this
looks
like
so
touching see how I'm leaning in
okay
now I'm going to show
[Music]
you the low box
squat and if you want to go and do a low
box
squat I'm going to adjust this to the
lowest
set which
is believe 11
[Music]
in let's see how this changes
things
so how can I keep vertical
shins if I'm like this and I go to sit
back sit back sit back sit back I can't
go deeper than
this I'm rounding my back if I keep an
arch I'd fall
backwards so you have to let the Shins I
can't lift it from here if I start
lifting from here I go backwards or I
can round my back like that that's not
what you want in a squat you want around
your back so when the low box squat you
do
not uh keep vertical shins your
shins will in fact be about level with
the front of the toes okay so when you
do a when you do a high box blat
parallel box spat you initiate with the
hips back you think sit back sit back
sit back with the low box squat you do
not think sit back you sit down think of
sitting your butt straight down and
staying pretty upright so again I still
have
the my calves touching the box and I
initiate by just sitting straight down
like this see I just popped I just screw
up because I'm my mind was used to the
higher box so I popped so that's bad
again the box is made of nails and I'm
trying to go
gently I don't like just
tapping I like actually sitting on it
pausing for a second pause relax the
muscles turn them on again I don't like
the big
rock like that I like the gentle Rock so
here's how it looks like with the
barbell uh with these you can do high
bar or low bar with the parallel I like
the low bar but with the low box squat
High bar is perfectly fine and exal
because it's more of a knee dominant
exercise but
uh I'll do high bar just to show it
so high bar
okay back with the calvs are
touching knees are out slight Rock back
tension is kept on the low back relax
the thighs and hips lean in
slightly come on
so I found that my beginners when I
teach them the box squat a lot of them
don't know how to sit back so for
powerlifting um some of my
clients um I'll give them four to six
weeks of box squats and then I switch
them back to free squatting and they set
PRS right away because in the power
squat you know the Olympic squat you've
got a narrow stance you might have on
weightlifting shoes which eled your heel
and you're super super upright and your
knees come forward you know in the
Olympic squat you're super upright but
in a powerlifting squat you tend to be a
little bit wider and you tend to sit
back a lot more and it's not uncommon
for torso lean to be 45° and with some
people who have maybe shorter to and
longer legs they can't even lean at more
of a 45 grle as long as they don't round
their back if they stay rigid you know
but once they learn the box squat you'll
switch them to free squatting and all of
a sudden they're sitting back more and
they're using their hips more and
they're getting you see the power out of
the hips and so I love the box squat
it's worked great for me and my clients
it's a very useful uh variation but
there are variations of box squats
and hopefully this video taught you a
thing or two so give it a try and let me
know what you think